<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> - Articles</title>
    <description>Passionate about making game developers more productive</description>
    <link>
    </link>
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Notes for 'What is USD: A Primer' SIGGRAPH 2019</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLDW Summary&lt;/strong&gt;: This talk is an intro to the key concepts and terminology of Universal Scene Description. The presentation shows examples of how USD is integrated into SideFX products.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /siggraph2019-what-is-usd-a-primer</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/siggraph2019-what-is-usd-a-primer</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Notes for &quot;Procedural World Generation of 'Far Cry 5'&quot; GDC2018</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLDW Summary&lt;/strong&gt;: This talk is about how FC5 developers created a pipeline for generating a realistic game world using procedural recipes. The talk contains a high-level overview of the pipeline with two deep dives into the details of the tools.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /gdc2018-procedural-world-generation-of-far-cry-5</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/gdc2018-procedural-world-generation-of-far-cry-5</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Notes for &quot;Tools for 'Marvel's Spider-Man' Editing with Immutable Data&quot; GDC2019</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLDW Summary&lt;/strong&gt;: This talk is a tour of the technologies that Insomniac Games developed to transition from their web based tools to their new desktop tools. Highlighting what challenges they encountered when replacing the tool chain in mid production.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2019 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /gdc2019-tools-for-marvels-spider-man-editing-with-immutable-data</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/gdc2019-tools-for-marvels-spider-man-editing-with-immutable-data</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Notes for &quot;The Future of Scene Description on 'God of War'&quot; GDC2019</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLDW Summary&lt;/strong&gt;: This talk sheds light on the decisions that were made by the Santa Monica Studio’s engine team while tackling the problems of time and complexity in transforming source data into game-ready data.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2019 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /gdc2019-the-future-of-scene-description-on-god-of-war</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/gdc2019-the-future-of-scene-description-on-god-of-war</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Notes for &quot;Bungie's Force Multipliers - Production Engineers&quot; GDC2019</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLDW Summary&lt;/strong&gt;: How Bungie organized a dedicated task force of engineers to stay on top of production challenges, blocking issues and shielding Tech-Artists and Engineers from random support requests.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2019 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /gdc2019-bungie-s-force-multipliers-production-engineers</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/gdc2019-bungie-s-force-multipliers-production-engineers</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Notes for &quot;Pipeline Support for Feature Branches in 'Destiny'&quot; GDC2019</title>
        
          <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldw-summary&quot;&gt;TLDW Summary:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How Bungie created an ecosystem of tools and workflows to allow small teams to quickly iterate on changes without worrying about breaking and blocking other teams.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /gdc2019-pipeline-support-for-feature-branches-in-destiny</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/gdc2019-pipeline-support-for-feature-branches-in-destiny</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Toolsmiths GDC 2019 Guide</title>
        
          <description>There are around 760+ sessions/tutorials/events at GDC 2019, finding the sessions that a tools developer would be interested in takes time. Below you will find a list of sessions that can become the base for your tools developer GDC 2019 experience, whether you plan on attending or you will be viewing post-factum.</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2019 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /toolsmiths-gdc-2019-guide</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/toolsmiths-gdc-2019-guide</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The origin of the path</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;After finishing the work on the first draft of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://thetoolsmiths.org/codex/learning_paths/tools_engineer_learning_path&quot;&gt;Tools Engineer Learning Path&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to write a short story behind the learning path and the thought process I went through when I was creating this resource.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /origin-of-the-path</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/origin-of-the-path</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Roles in Game Tools Development</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Today in Game Development there are several roles that take part in creating new Game Tools and developing the existing ones. Depending on the number of people in a Game Development team multiple roles may be assigned to one responsible person. It would be challenging if not impossible to find a studio/company that has a dedicated person assigned to each of the roles listed. In this post, I will list the main roles and give them a short definition.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2019 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /tool-development-roles</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/tool-development-roles</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Notes for &quot;A Tale of Three Data Schemas&quot;</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;GDC 2018, Tools Tutorial Day, Ludovic Chabant, Senior Software Engineer @ Electronic Arts Vancouver shared the know-how of the Frostbite engine team when it comes to designing the game’s data.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2018 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /tools-tutorial-day-a-tale-of-three-data-schemas</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/tools-tutorial-day-a-tale-of-three-data-schemas</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The efficiency ratio for game tools improvements</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last Update on July 22nd, 2018&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2018 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /the-efficiency-ratio-for-game-tools-improvements</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/the-efficiency-ratio-for-game-tools-improvements</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Toolsmiths Codex Launch</title>
        
          <description>It’s not always easy to find information regarding Game Tools Development on the Internet. There isn't just one place where you can go and find information regarding a particular topic. With the insight and knowledge of The Toolsmiths Community, with developers from around the world, we have made an excellent online resource for Game Tools Developers, and it is called The Toolsmiths Codex.</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Mar 2018 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /toolsmiths-codex-launch</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/toolsmiths-codex-launch</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Toolsmiths GDC 2018 Guide</title>
        
          <description>There are around 650+ sessions at this year's GDC, and it isn't easy to find sessions that you as a tools developer might enjoy. I have tried to find and collect most of the talks that a tools developer would be interested in attending or watching after the fact.</description>
        
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2018 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /toolsmiths-gdc-2018-guide</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/toolsmiths-gdc-2018-guide</guid>
      </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
